Okay, so in this video then,
we are going to discuss the
differences between centralised
and decentralized contracting.
Okay, so first of all, what is centralized
and decentralized contracting?
Well, centralized contractor
means that you have one
central procurement
department in your organization.
There is one procurement department,
right?
And all procurement activities has to go
through this one procurement department.
And that's a centralized.
Whereas in a decentralized environment,
right?
There is no procurement department.
You have a procurement
manager on your project
or a procurement officer on your project.
There is no central procurement department
as such that you have to go through.
Okay.
So these are the two extremes.
In a centralized, you have one central
procurement department.
In a decentralized, there is no
Now, in the exam, they will always ask you
about these two.
extremes.
In reality, many organisations are going
to fall somewhere in between, right?
You may have elements of centralised and
elements of decentralised, or you may be
more towards one side versus another side,
or it might be a mixture of the two.
But for the exam, generally, it's going to
be either you're purely 100% centralized
or you purely 100% decentralized,
right?
So they're going to be asking about the
two extremes.
All right, so let's talk about some of the
advantages and disadvantages of each one.
So let's talk about centralized first.
So again, remember, in a centralized
procurement or centralized contracting,
you have one procurement department,
all procurement activities must go through
this one centralized procurement
department.
So since it is a procurement department,
it's a procurement department,
it's a procurement of contracting
expertise.
You have procurement managers,
procurement officers, you have a
procurement officers, you
have an entire department,
they're just dedicated to
contracts, to procurement.
They are, for those employees,
there's standard career progression.
So it's an entire department of expertise.
And because it's a centralized department,
because it's a department of contracting
expertise, there's standardized practices,
standardized procedures.
Everybody knows, the entire organization
knows what the procedures are and,
you know, as a project
manager, you don't need
to worry too much about
procurement activities.
Everything is done by the centralized
procurement department.
So you don't have to
spend as much time looking
at contracts, negotiating
contracts, right?
You don't have to worry about terms and
conditions as much.
Procurement department takes care of all
of that.
So those are the biggest advantages of
having a centralized procurement department.
What about some of the disadvantage?
Some of you may have experienced this.
Those of you that work for larger
organizations and you have a centralized
procurement department, or at least some
kind of centralized procurement
department, good luck getting hold to
someone when you actually need them.
That's the biggest disadvantage.
There is nobody dedicated to your project.
There's no procurement
officer, procurement
manager that is actually
dedicated to your project.
So you can't always get hold of someone
whenever you need them.
You're based on their schedule.
So, you know, staff isn't always
available.
And each time you might get a different
staff, right, a different procurement
manager or a different procurement
officer.
Each time you might
have to explain the same
thing over and over again
and so on and so forth.
because there's nobody dedicated to your
project.
So that is alleviated then in a
decentralized contracting environment.
And in a decentralized contracting,
you have one procurement manager or one
procurement officer that is dedicated to
your project.
They are dedicated to your project.
They're just working on your project.
There is no central procurement department
in this case.
Or you as a project manager may be the
procurement manager.
So, the advantage there is, there's always
somebody available, right, there's always
someone there, procurement staff,
there's someone dedicated to your project,
right?
There's always someone
there whenever you need
them for any kind of
procurement activities.
Also, project manager then has more
control over these activities.
So the project manager has more control.
They have more control over the timeline,
right, over what can be negotiated,
or rather over what is negotiated,
they have more control over when we're
going to be conducting procurement
activities, right, you don't have to wait
for a procurement officer, so because
there's always somebody dedicated.
The biggest disadvantage, though,
in a decentralized environment is
basically you're limited to your own
experience or you're limited to the
procurement manager's experience,
right?
Whoever the procurement officer is,
the procurement staff, right?
They're dedicated to
your project, but you're just
limited to their experience
because there is no central
procurement department
that they can go back to.
Or if you are the procurement officer,
right, you as a project manager,
if you're the procurement manager,
then you're limited to your experience.
And so you must develop contracting
experience as you go along.
So these are some of the
advantages and disadvantages
then of centralized versus decentralized.
In reality, though, remember, many
organizations, right, will be.
either swaying more to
one side or more to the
other side, or there might
be a mixture of the two.
You don't necessarily always have,
you know, the two extremes.
So I have a very simple example.
I've worked for a couple of large global
consulting firms.
So we're traveling around to Fortune 100
clients implementing their IT systems,
implementing the HR systems.
Well, you can imagine then, you know,
a large global consulting firm,
they would have many procurement
departments, right?
They'd have several procurement
departments, but then for each one of our
projects, any of our large projects,
we would have one dedicated procurement
officer that would be a centralized and a
decentralized environment.
And then sometimes if it's a very large
project, we would have one procurement
officer specifically dedicated to our
project or another project.
So maybe a procurement
officer that was dedicated
to, you know, two or
three different projects.
Again, a mixture, a mixture of centralized
and decentralized.
But again, for the exam,
remember, if they ask you a
question, generally it's going
to be one of the two extremes.
Either purely centralized environment or a
purely decentralized environment.
Okay.